American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5001 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Correspondence: 1913, Feb 7 - Aug 31. (Reel 9)
  Anthrax infection and the need for legislation to protect tanners, shoe factory employees, and others against this disease attracted grow-ing interest. A comprehensive study in this area was begun. Lack of money limited efforts to investigate other industrial diseases, and John Andrews approached John D. Rockefeller unsuccessfully in an attempt to obtain funds.
- Correspondence: 1913, Sept 1 - 1914, Jan 21., 1913-1914 (Reel 10)
  The emergence of sickness insurance (health insurance) as a major concern of the AALL dominates this period. Joseph Chamberlain outlined a suggested survey of European sickness insurance (1/7/14) to be made prior to the AALL's investigation of the situation in the United States. Many meetings of the Association's sickness insurance committee were held. I. M. Rubinow wrote often in reference to drafting a standard bill (a prototype legislative bill on a specific issue) on sickness insurance. There was some controversy over whether or not it should be compulsory, and P. Tecumseh Shermam resigned because of the disagreement (1/9/14). An interesting letter (9/16/13) to Henry Seager and Henry W. Farnam describes Andrews' visit to the Cripple Creek Mine, the mine owner's blacklist, a meeting with "Mother" Jones, and the growing conservatism of the Western Federation of Miners. Irene Osgood Andrews wrote the report on minimum wage legislation in New York State. In December (12/24/13) Andrews wrote again to Gompers, asking for an apology. Andrews became interested in another problem of working conditions and wrote often to Thomas J. Parkinson of the Columbia University Legislative Drafting Department and others in regard to revision of the compressed air provisions of the New York State labor laws.
- Correspondence: 1914, Jan 22 - June 18. (Reel 11)
  The Association sponsored the "Kern Bill" introduced in Congress by its sponsor, Congressman John Kern, providing workmen's compensation for federal employees in the District of Columbia. Royal Meeker and I. M. Rubinow were in partial disagreement as to certain sections of the bill and frequently wrote to Andrews about it. Throughout January and February, plans were made for the National Conference on Unemployment that was to be held in New York City (2/27/28). In addition, the growing problem of unemployment sparked many surveys and reports. The meetings of the Sickness Insurance Committee continued. Andrews defended the AALL's impartiality on "unionism" to James Emery (2/26/14) and disclaimed any interest in labor-management disputes beyond the questions of health and safety. Mid-March saw John and Irene Andrews working together on a survey of free employment bureaus, and for the passage of a free employment agency bill in the New York State Legislature. In June, Andrews began to prepare for the European Congresses of the IALL by writing reports on United States labor legislation, unemployment, social insurance and industrial disease.
- Correspondence: 1914, June 19 - Oct 31. (Reel 12)
  The commencement of World War I affected the Association drastically, The IALL congresses were cancelled and funds that had been available to further the work of the AALL were diverted to war relief. But sickness insurance and unemployment were still major issues. Frederick Hoffman, who had been active on the Sickness Insurance Committee of the AALL reported himself upset over the principle of compulsory insurance. Katherine Coman suggested (8/13/14) that the committee stress prevention as well as relief, a change that was soon made. Many requests for help in drafting workmen's compensation laws were received from all over the United States during this period. Andrews was busy on a study of occupational anthrax in the United States. In the fall, a study of the effect of lead poisoning on workers was begun, using the Brooklyn Bridge painters as a test group. Walter Lippmann interviewed Andrews on the unemployment problem in October for a special issue of the New Republic. John R. Commons and Andrews consulted frequently on their book, Principles of Labor Legislation.
- Correspondence: 1914, Nov 1 - 1915, Mar 8., 1914-1915 (Reel 13)
  The problems of unemployment and health insurance continued to occupy most of the Association's time. Enclosed in a letter from Joseph Chamberlain (12/11/14) was an eleven-page draft of the health insurance act which the AALL was promoting, annotated by Andrews. Andrews served on the Board of the Municipal Lodging House and much of the correspondence concerns its operation. In late January the Association's standard bill for the regulation of compressed air work was issued.
- Correspondence: 1915, Mar 9 - Aug 18. (Reel 14)
  Andrews continued to work daily on health insurance. Most of the correspondence deals with this bill. At the end of May, Samuel Gompers resigned as Associate Vice President. There is commentary on this event from several people, including an undated letter (circa June) from Milton Fairchild to Henry Seager, in which he reports that: "Gompers says he has changed the name of the Association to the Ameri-can Association for the Assassination of Labor Legislation." John Andrews' letter to James Maurer (7/12/15) is an excellent example of the strategy employed by the Association in exploiting emo-tions to explain the need for their legislation. This letter deals with the death of two "sand hogs" who were buried alive in an accident that "...could not have occurred if our bill for the protection of compressed air workers had been in force in Pennsylvania." On August 9, a series of letters and a questionnaire on relief of unemployment through public work was sent out. Replies were received for the next several months.
- Correspondence: 1915, Aug 19 - Dec 31. (Reel 15)
  The modification of AALL's standard bill on health insurance con-tinued to occupy much of the organization's attention. On November 12 the draft of the AALL act for health insurance was released, and in December John Andrews wrote Dr. Henry Favill (AMA), thanking him for his cooperation in the preparation of the bill. The bill to provide workmen's compensation for federal employees in the District of Columbia, now known in the correspondence as the Kern-McGillicuddy Bill, was still being pushed, but with little success.
- Correspondence: 1916, Jan 1 - Apr 21. (Reel 16)
  John Andrews sent Samuel McCune Lindsay the tentative program for 1916 (1/7/16), providing an excellent synopsis of the year's work. The program on social insurance was to stress workmen's compensation, health insurance and unemployment insurance. Accident and disease reporting, support for the federal bill for a Museum of Safety, and the urging of passage of the standard bill for compressed air workers and a cleanliness bill for lead workers were to dominate the industrial safety and hygiene phase of the Association's work. To meet the abuses of the so-called continuous industries, a one-day-rest-in-seven bill was advocated, as was the three-shift system. Finally, the Association was to urge reorganization of state labor bureaus, especially in Kentucky, Maryland, and New Jersey, as a means of making the administration of existent labor legislation more effective. The health insurance standard bill was introduced in Albany and Boston. John Randolph Haynes approached Andrews (1/29/16) and volunteered a substantial contribution if the AALL would make coal mine safety the first priority of its program. Through May, Royal Meeker, Middleton Beaman, and others worked with the Association in urging passage of the Kern-McGillicuddy Bill (workmen's compensation for District of Columbia). In April, Andrews testified before the United States House of Representatives Committee on Labor in favor of the establishment of a Commission for Investigating Social Insurance. Frederick Hoffman resigned from the Association in a letter to Irving Fisher, in protest against the AALL's insistence upon compulsory health insurance.
- Correspondence: 1916, Apr 22 - 1917, June 30., 1916-1917 (Reel 17)
  Intensive lobbying for health insurance continued as Andrews con-ducted a campaign to raise funds for its promotion with the slogan, "Health First." The Association supported legislative bills for health insurance in New York and Michigan. On the federal level, the AALL's most important piece of legislation was the Kern-McGillicuddy Bill. In May, John Andrews sent AALL staffer Irene Sylvester to Washington to act as the Association's lobbyist. Her informal letters to the New York office, reporting on the progress of the bill, give examples of how one congressman put pressure on another to insure his vote. In June, when she complained of discouragement, Andrews wrote to her, "Cheer Up! Morbid depression is an occupational disease among those who are obliged to be pleasant to Congressmen." (6/5/17) In late August, Andrews was able to inform the AALL members that the bill had passed the Senate and that "...we can now concentrate even greater effort on our campaign for universal health insurance." Paul H. Douglas advised Andrews that since war seemed inevitable, the Association should adopt a policy of guarding against exploitation of workers in time of war (4/1/17) .. John Andrews initiated a special series of bulletins, Labor Laws in War Time. Communication with the IALL offices in Europe became virtually impossible.
- Correspondence: 1917, July 1 - 1918, Dec 9., 1917-1918 (Reel 18)
  Under the pressure of the war effort, demands for health insurance were de-emphasized, while problems created by the emergency came to the fore. The United States Department of Labor War Policies Board sent Andrews policy memoranda for review in late August. In December of 1916, Andrews advised Senator Joseph Robinson (12/6/17) that the legislation providing for federal public employment offices which he was to introduce should be pushed as a war emergency measure. This is referred to as the Robinson-Keating Bill in later letters., Gompers, largely out of touch with the Association, telegraphed an invitation to Andrews to attend the American Federation of Labor Employment Problems Conference. A form letter to members (12/19/17) outlined the program for 1918, which included war emergency measures, Federal Public Employment Ser-vice, health insurance, and labor adjustment. In mid-January 1918, Charles Barnes, Irving Fisher, Royal Meeker, V. Everitt Macy and Edward Keating all wrote to Andrews, urging him to take the lead in the fight for the Robinson- Keating Bill. Irene Osgood Andrews became very much involved in efforts to organize the Maternity Center in New York City. Many state federations of labor wrote for advice on health insurance, and in the fall, the AALL worked for workmen's compensation in Maine, Arkansas and North Dakota.
- Correspondence: 1918, Dec 10 - 1919, Apr 30., 1918-1919 (Reel 19)
  A letter from Andrews to New York State senators (12/18/18) set forth the Association's objectives for 1919, including an amendment of workmen's compensation legislation to exclude profit-making insurance companies, universal workingman's health insurance, and a minimum wage for women. In early January, Henry Sterling sent a copy of the workmen's compensation act which he had prepared for the American Federation of Labor to Andrews for his criticism. Letters were received from IALL staff members Sophy Sanger and Stephen Bauer, trying to re-establish communications. Frances Perkins, Commissioner of the New York State Industrial Commission, wrote to ask for information on maternity insurance, and later wrote to Irene Andrews for John's views on health insurance. Irene Sylvester, now Mrs. Walston Chubb, was sent by the Associa-tion to Albany to lobby for the Donahue-Davenport health insurance bill. In March 1919, a new standard bill for workmen's compensation was issued, based on that of the state of Ohio and on federal legis-lation. Irene Andrews wrote Sophy Sanger (4/2/19) that she expected to be in London in April to tour maternity centers, and that John would be in London later that summer.
- Correspondence: 1919, May 1 - Nov 25. (Reel 20)
  John Andrews sailed for Europe in mid-July to further the work of the Association for the educational commission of the United States War Department. The trip also provided the opportunity for him to serve as technical advisor to the organizing committee appointed by the federal government to set up the International Labor Legislation Conference scheduled for October in Washington. On his return in September, Andrews sent John R. Commons a report of his trip, and stated that he expected to spend most of his time that fall in Washington. S. S. Goldwater and Alexander Lambert of the American Medical Association cooperated with the AALL to launch another drive for health insurance.
- Correspondence: 1919, Nov 26. - 1920, Mar 31., 1919-1920 (Reel 21)
  Health insurance was being attacked as "un-American" by the newly formed New York League for Americanism, and the Association's attention focused on combating this opposition. Dr. Alexander Lambert, President of the AMA, wrote John Andrews (1/28/20), "I think that my profession will get over its present state of hysteria (over health insurance) just as my ancestors got over the Salem witchcraft." The federal employee retirement bill, known as the Sterling-Lehblach Bill, was energetically promoted throughout the spring. I. M. Rubinow was in Palestine during this period, and his scattered letters reported on the Zionist movement.
- Correspondence: 1920, Apr 1 - Sept 25. (Reel 22)
  The Fess-Kenyon Bill for the vocational rehabilitation of industrial cripples replaced health insurance as the center of concern of the Association during this period, although it was still fighting the charges of "un-Americanism" in regard to the latter. The problem of workmen's compensation for longshoremen and seamen was studied, and there was correspondence with union leaders, including Andrew Furuseth, and with T. V. O'Connor on this subject. The Federal Employee Retirement Bill (Sterling-Lehblach) was passed in late May. Many people wrote to congratulate Andrews on the Association's role in securing its passage. Unemployment insurance was again an issue, and Andrews suggested to J. J. Handley (9/24/20) that the Wisconsin State Federation of Labor try to sponsor an unemployment insurance bill in its state.
- Correspondence: 1920, Sept 27 - 1921, Feb 24., 1920-1921 (Reel 23)
  Unemployment was the primary focus of activities in the later half of 1920 and the first months of 1921. Thomas Chadbourne, President of the AALL, sent Governor Nathan Miller a nine and one half page report from the Association on the need for an unemployment insurance investigating committee in New York State. Otto Mallery reported on his efforts to promote public employment for the relief of the unemployed. The program for 1921 included maternity protection, one-day-rest-in-seven, rehabilitation of industrial cripples, and reasonable work hours. As the federal bill to provide workmen's compensation was before Congress, Irene Sylvester Chubb was again sent to Washington to act as the Association's lobbyist.
- Correspondence: 1921, Dec 8 - 1922, Mar 3., 1921-1922 (Reel 24)
  Workmen's compensation for seamen, longshoremen, and private employees in the District of Columbia continued to provide an important activity for the Association. Joseph Chamberlain and Miles Dawson worked together closely on the longshoremen's bill, and the Association cooperated with Congressman Roy G. Fitzgerald on the bill to provide workmen's compensation for private employees in the District. On several occasions John Andrews lobbied in Washington for support of the Fitzgerald Bill. John Randolph Haynes again approached the organization, offering funds if the AALL would work on coal mine safety. John Andrews replied (5/31/21) that "$1000 will mean a vigorous campaign for mine safety that fall." In September, Herbert Hoover invited Andrews to attend conferences on unemployment in Washington, and Andrews was active for some time as a member of the Economic Advisory Committee of the United States Department of Commerce.
- Correspondence: 1921, Dec 8 - 1922, Mar 3. (continued), 1921-1922 (Reel 25)
  Federal bills for workmen's compensation for longshoremen and for workers in the District of Columbia continued to receive most of the Association's attention, along with efforts to secure the adoption by individual states of an exclusive state fund for workmen's compensation. The Association was opposed to discrimination against the non-resident dependents of aliens in allotting compensation. Many advocates of the Kenyon Bill for long-range planning of public works sought Andrews' support. The blanket equality amendment of the National Women's Party and coal mine safety also received attention in the early months of 1922.
- Correspondence: 1922, Mar 4 - June 30. (Reel 26)
  The Fitzgerald Bill, the child labor amendment, and coal mine safety were of primary importance to the AALL throughout the spring of 1922. Irene Andrews continued to be involved with the Maternity Center and with bills for maternity protection. A five-page, handwritten letter from Felix Frankfurter to Andrews (5/29/22) questions whether there should be any federal labor legislation at all, and discusses the child labor amendment and the practice of "constitution tinkering" in general.
- Correspondence: 1922, Jul 1 - Dec 15. (Reel 27)
  Irene Sylvester Chubb was sent again to Washington to lobby for the Fitzgerald bill for workmen's compensation. John Andrews worked closely with Gifford Pinchot, newly elected Governor of Pennsylvania, on many issues relative to labor law administration. Abraham Epstein wrote that he had become associated with the Eagles fraternal organization and would be working with Frank Hering on old age pensions (9/11/22). Louis Varlez (9/21/22) and Stephen Bauer (12/9/22) wrote that the IALL missed the cooperation of the American branch, and urged Andrews to work for unification of all the international organizations interested in social progress. The program for 1923 emphasized a living wage, unemployment relief, mine accident prevention, and workmen's compensation.
- Correspondence: 1922, Dec 16 - 1923, Oct 31., 1922-1923 (Reel 28)
  In addition to the programs planned for 1923, a heavy emphasis on old age pensions and insurance dominated the work of the Association. Columbia University Legislative Drafting Bureau sent John Andrews (1/12/23) the program of the AALL for old age pensions that had been worked out in cooperation with the Eagles. Abraham Epstein wrote often during the early months of the year on the progress of the old age pension bill and Gomper's attitude toward it. Epstein's personal dissatisfaction with his job is evidenced in his April correspondence. Felix Frankfurter wrote to Andrews (6/18/23) in regard to his def-inition of law enforcement. Herbert Hoover wrote in late August to invite Andrews to serve as an informal observer at the International Unemployment Association Conference in Luxembourg that fall. Sidney Hillman explained the workings of his union's private unem-ployment insurance contract (9/26/23). During the summer months, special efforts were made to fight discrimination in granting workmen's compensation awards to the non-resident dependents of aliens.
- Correspondence: 1923, Nov 1 - 1924, June 5., 1923-1924 (Reel 29)
  Attention to the question of coal mine safety increased, along with the longshoremen's workmen's compensation, old age pensions, and industrial diseases. Irene Sylvester Chubb lobbied for the Fitzgerald Bill from January through May, 1924, and wrote frequently about her activities. Correspondence was carried on with the American Mining Congress and the Mining Safety Coordinating Committee. H. Foster Bain, Stephen Wise, E. A. Holbrook and William Green communicated on the coal mine safety program and urged Andrews to continue this campaign. In April, Alice Hamilton wrote concerning new problems of phosphorous poisoning in fireworks plants in New Jersey.
- Correspondence: 1924, June 6 - 1925, Feb 8., 1924-1925 (Reel 30)
  The Association continued to be concerned about industrial disease and accidents, particularly those relating to radium poisoning and mine safety. Katherine Wiley wrote Andrews about several girls who died after being employed to paint radium on watch faces, and enclosed several letters which gave details of the case (6/19/24). Andrews suggested to Ethelbert Steward (6/19/24) that the Bureau of Labor Statistics should investigate the problem of phosphorous poison in the fireworks industry and the radium poison cases. Correspondence with E. A. Holbrook, the American Mining Congress and the Mining Standardization Coordinating Committee continued to emphasize coal dusting and general mine safety. Henri Fuss wrote about the merger of the IALL and other international associations with the International Association for Social Progress (IASP) (7/10/24). Andrews asked Herbert Hoover if the government would be willing to pay his passage to the IASP Congress, but Hoover replied (9/8/24) that, although he would like Andrews to be the government's informal representative, there were no funds available to support this trip. Ida Tarbell wrote John Andrews in 1925 that she expected to write a piece on coal dusting: "This is not merely to save face with you but because I would like to do something, even if so very little, to help push the matter."
- Correspondence: 1925, Feb 9 - July 21. (Reel 31)
  Labor law administration was the dominant issue of this period. The problems of the administration of workmen's compensation and the increased use of "yellow dog" contracts became a serious concern. Attention was also given to improving workmen's compensation standards, James Lynch, the President of the International Typographers Union, proposed a nationwide campaign for workmen's compensation reform through the AALL and the American Federation of Labor (2/23/25).
- Correspondence: 1925, Aug 1 - 1926, Jan 26., 1925-1926 (Reel 32)
  The Epstein-Andrews split over Abraham Epstein's organization of a new national association advocating old age pensions began in December, 1925. Worth M. Tippy of the Federal Council of Churches requested John Andrews' assessment of Abraham Epstein and his ideas after Tippy was approached to back Epstein's new national organiza-tion. The program for 1926 was prepared in late November and included the fight for "real wages", reduction of waste in industry, workmen's compensation, accident prevention, and unemployment relief. The area of special interest in workmen's compensation during late 1925 and early 1926 was the passage of legislation to protect interstate workers, especially longshoremen and seamen. Anthony Chlopek of the longshoremen and Andrew Furuseth of the seamen were the Association's chief union contacts. Throughout January and February, several criticisms of the AALL's newest federal longshoremen's and interstate workers' compensation bill were received? those from Charles Verrill (1/18/26), Frederick Wilcox (1/20/26), and Frances Perkins (2/4/26) are especially significant.
- Correspondence: 1926, Jan 27 - 1926, June 18. (Reel 33)